

## **MUHAMMAD ILHAM ALI**

#### CHEMICAL ENGINEERING FRESH GRADUATE

Phone : +62 812 9610 5302

E-mail : <u>ilhamali.pane@gmail.com</u>
Linkedin : linkedin.com/in/ilhamalipane

Address : Perumahan Taman Ciruas Permai, Blok E2 No.1, Ciruas,

Serang, Banten Province

Motivated young professional with an exemplary academic record and passion to progress in chemical process industries. Involved on local and international organization focused on chemical engineer competencies, which trained leadership, communication, and well-organized team. On his 3rd year of Study, he joined internship as Jr. Process Engineer and started his first career as Jr. Process Safety Engineer which enrich his knowledge in engineering & design in Facility and made him as an excellent participant on industrial fields.

## AREA OF COMPETENCIES

Engineering and Technology

Process Modelling and Simulation

Software Simulation

Safety in Facility

**Critical Thinking** 

- Corrosion Study
- Hazard Identification

Leadership

Strategic Planning

Software Ability: Aspen Hysys, Matlab, Phast, ECE, Matlab, Ms. Office

### **EXPERIENCE**

**JANUARY 2021-SEPTEMBER 2021** 

#### JR. PROCESS SAFETY ENGINEER, PT SYNERGY ENGINEERING

Joined as Junior Process Safety Engineer. As seven months of work in there, he had completed several kinds of work in safety-related jobs in designing onshore & offshore facility, include of providing:

- Safety Sign Layout Drawing
- Escape Route and Safety Equipment Layout Drawing
- Hazardous Area Classification (HAC) Schedule and Drawing
- Induced Vibration Report
- Noise Study Report
- Non-Flammable Hazard Assessment Report
- Fire Zone Study
- Fire and Explosion Risk Assessment

Also contributed as Material & Corrosion Engineer which provide:

- Corrosion Simulation using ECE software
- Provide Material Selection based on Corrosion Analysis in Equipment, Piping, and Pipeline
- Provide Material Selection Diagram (MSD)
- Develop Material and Corrosion Specification

Contributed in 6 projects of gas processing facility by performing safety analysis and develop recommendation to ensure compliance with international standards such as API, ISO, NFPA, OGP, E&I, ASME, NACE, and also by using safety and corrosion related software.

#### **JUNE 2019-AUGUST 2019**

#### PROCESS ENGINEER INTERNS, PT PUSTEK E&T

Joined internship at EPC company as process division team. At three months of work in there, he works as same as the other process engineers staff and with guidance from multi-disciple engineering team on there and gained much engineering experience such as creating Pre-Feasibility Study documents and Engineering Design Report. With responsibilities such as:

- Drafting process ideas as the first involved engineering discipline
- Design and Perform process simulations, as reactive process, or pipeline gas stream

- Offering and selecting desired process with safety and quality standards
- Providing process engineering documents and standard operating procedures
  Finishing up 7 activities as junior engineer at PT Pustek Projects, with most discipline at natural
  gas processing: distribution, metering, and dehydration, Nitrogen separation with PSA
  technology, and Pre-FS of methanol production from natural gas

## **EDUCATION**

2016-2020

## BACHELOR OF CHEM.ENGINEERING, INSTITUT TEKNOLOGI SEPULUH

NOPFMBFR

Fresh Graduate of Chemical Engineering Department ITS, with overall GPA 3.64. As of now, he had completing two of his final year thesis include of :

- Preliminary Plant Design of Methanol Production from Natural Gas Feed, at AA-Grade
  of Methanol with adapting Autothermal reforming as synthetic gas processing and
  multi-tubular methanol reactor.
- Simulation Research, Study of Hydrodynamic and Mass Transfer in Sieve Tray Column without Downcomer with addition of Circular Calming Trip using Computational Fluid Dynamic (CFD), which aims to study the performance of sieve tray with and without modifications of calming strip to hydrodynamic phenomena and separation effectiveness of the separation column

## **ACTIVITIES**

FEB 2017-APRIL 2018

## STAFF OF COMPETENCY DEVELOPMENT, HIMPUNAN MHS. TEKNIK KIMIA ITS

Engaged in hard skill and soft skill competency developing for the chemical engineering students in ITS. With responsibilities such as: design and facilitate chem-eng competency, he then entrusted to handle issue developments field to increase the student's awareness on careers and engineering issues with its output study.

Held Strategic Issue Study: Future of Renewable Energy in Indonesia

JUN 2018-AUG 2019

## **DIRECTOR OF PROFESSIONAL DEVELOPMENT, AICHE ITS STUDENT CHAPTER**

Responsible for planning and arrange various activities which aims to promote and spread awareness by held professionalism programs. As student chapter, we had affiliation with other worldwide student chapter and association with professional member. Provide insight of internship, software skills, and international conference held by AIChE.

 Made up to 4 new projects and 2 weekly agenda that focused on chemical engineer fields. As the results as our AIChE SC great teamwork, we received an Outstanding Student Chapter Award, which shows exceptional level of participation, professionalism, program quality, and its involvement in university and community

JUN 2018-MAR 2019

## **COORDINATOR OF EXPERT TEAM, NOPEC COMPETITION**

Volunteered as a junior expert team on 2018 that responsible to provide and scores the exams for NOPEC (National Olympiad of Chemical Engineering) competition in term of Mathematic, Physic, Chemistry, and Basic Chemical Engineering. then lead as a coordinator of expert teams on the next year.

• Improved the exams level with more advancing on chemical engineering insight with basic knowledge from high school education

## LANGUAGE COMPETENCIES

• ENGLISH: Intermediate, with TOEFL ITP Score 537

• INDONESIA : Native



South Tangerang, September 6th, 2021

No: 041/SYN-ADM/HR/SKK/IX/2021 Re: Working Experience Reference

## **TO WHOM IT MAY CONCERN**

The undersigned hereby truly certifies that:

Name

Muhammad Ilham Ali Pane

Working Period:

January 29st 2021 - September 6th 2021

He has been employed by PT Synergy Engineering, as Jr. Process Safety Engineer. We acknowledge that during the above said period he performed his duties in a good manner.

At all time he's able to handle major responsibilities and we found him to be a highly committed team player.

We recommend him for the future and hope for his success in the future.

Sincerely Yours, PT Synergy Engineering

PT. Synergy Engineering

Rosza Maya Melinda Human Resources Management

No.





## INSTITUT TEKNOLOGI SEPULUH NOPEMBER

Terakreditasi A oleh BAN-PT, SK No. 288/SK/BAN-PT/Akred/PT/XI/2018

memberikan

kepada:

## Muhammad Ilham Ali

Nomor Pokok Mahasiswa: 02211640000039 Nomor Induk Kependudukan: 3604092708980001 Lahir di Serang, tanggal 27 Agustus 1998

pada tanggal 28 Agustus 2020 telah menyelesaikan Pendidikan Sarjana (S1) Program Studi Teknik Kimia

(Terakreditasi A oleh BAN-PT, SK No. 0832/SK/BAN-PT/Akred/S/VI/2016)

berhak menyandang gelar

## SARJANA TEKNIK (S.T.)

Diterbitkan di Surabaya pada tanggal 4 September 2020

DEKAN Fakultas Teknologi Industri dan Rekayasa Sistem

> Dr. Wawan Aries Widodo, S.T., M.T. 1478 NIP 19710405 199702 1 001



REKTOR

TT2.IX.2/PP.06.02/ UN NOU 2020

les Widodo, ST., MT.

Fakultas Teknologan dustra dan Rekayasa Sistem ITS

Prof. Dr. Ir. Mochamad Ashari, M.Eng. NIP 19651012 199003 1 003

## INSTITUT TEKNOLOGI SEPULUH NOPEMBER TRANSKRIP / ACADEMIC TRANSCRIPT



Mala Kuliah

**FAKULTAS TEKNOLOGI INDUSTRI DAN REKAYASA SISTEM** 

Program Studi / Study Program Nama / Name

NRP / ID No

: Teknik Kimia / Chemical Engineering

: 02211640000039

: Muhammad Ilham Ali

Indeks Prestasi / GPA : 3.64 Tahun Masuk / Entrance Year : 2016 Tahun Lulus / Graduation Year: 2020

Lama Studi / Length of Study : 8 semester

Predikat / Predicate : Cum Laude / Cum Laude

Nomor Ijazah / Diploma No

: 242012020000775

Mata Kullah

Subject

Sem Kr Nilal

Sem Cr Grade

FACULTY OF INDUSTRIAL TECHNOLOGY
AND SYSTEMS ENGINEERING

Sem Kr Nilai No

Kode

Tempat, Tanggal Lahir / : Serang 27 Agustus 1998 Place, Date of Birth

: Sarjana Teknik (S.T.) Gelar / Degree Sem Kr Nilal No Kode
Sem Cr Grade No Code Mata Kullah

-	Code	Subject			Grade	1	Code	Subject			Grade	1	Cooe	Subject	6		A
1	KG14110	1 Pendidikan Agama Islam	1	2	A	21	T1184415	Ekonomi Teknik	4	3	AB	4	UG184915	Teknopreneur	0	-	
		Religion						Engineering Economy				1		Technopreneurship	7		-
2	IG14110	6 Wawasan Kebangsaan	1	3	A	22	TK141241	Mikrobiologi Industri	4	3	AB	42	SK184764	Geokimia dan Mineralogi	/	3	Α.
		Crics						Industrial Microbiology						Geochemistry and Mineralogy	-	-	-
3	IG14110	7 Wawasan Teknologi dan Komunikasi limlah	1	3	A	23	TK141341	Matematika Teknik Kirnia II	4	3	AB	43	SK184766	Kimia Bahan Makanan	7	3	A
		Technology and Scientific Communication						Chemical Engineering Mathematics II						Food Chemistry			
4	IG14110	6 Bahasa Inggris	1	3	В	24	TK141342	Azas Teknik Kimia II	4	3	AB	44	TK184701	Pengolahan Limbah Industri	7	3	BC
		English						Chemical Engineering Principles II						Industrial Waste Treatment			
5	SF14120	11 Frsika Dasar I	1	4	A	25	TK141343	Operasi Teknik Kimla I	4	3	A	45	TK184702	Sintesa dan Simulasi Proses	7	3	AB
		Basic Physics I						Chemical Engineering Operation I						Synthesis and Process Simulation			
6	SK14120	7 Kerna Dasar	1	2	AB	26	TK141344	Thermodinamika Teknik Kimla I	4	3	AB	46	TK184703	Desain Pabrik Kirnia dan Ekonomi	7	4	AB
	1	Chemistry		T				Chemical Engineering Thermodynamics I						Plant Design and Economic			
7	SM14120	3 Kalkulus I	1	3	A	27	TK141345	Proses Perpindahan II	4	3	A	47	TK184704	Tugas Penelitian	7	6	A
	1	Celculus I						Transport Processes II				1		Research Project			
8	TK14121	1 Program Komputer	1	12	В	28	TK141346	Bahan Konstruksi dan Korosi	4	2	A	48	TK184801	Keselamatan Pabrik Kimia	8	3	8
_		Computer Programming						Material Of Construction & Corrosion				1		Chemical Plant Salety			
g	SF141204	4 Frsika Dasar II	2	3	A	29	TK184405	Thermodinamika Teknik Kimia II	4	3	BC	49	TK184802	Keria Praktek	8	12	A
ŕ		Basic Physics II						Chemical Engineering Thermodynamics II				1	111111111111111111111111111111111111111	On Job Training	-	+-	
10	SM14120	4 Kalisalus II	2	3	A	30	TK141351	Teknik Reaksi Kimla I	5	13	A	50	TK184803	Tugas Desain Pabrik Kimia	8	6	A
	-	Calculus II						Chemical Reaction Engineering I				1	1	Plant Design Project	-	+	
11	TK141221	Penganiar industri Kimia	. 2	2	AB	31	TK184502	Aplikasi Teknik Kimia I	5	12	8	1		, manager rajest		1	
-		Introduction To Industrial Chemistry						Chemical Engineering Application I		1		11				1	
12	TK141222	Kirnia Organik I	2	2	A	32	TK184503	Operasi Teknik Kimla II	5	3	AB	11				+	
		Organic Chemistry I						Unit Operations II		1	1	11				+	
13	TK141223	Kerna Analisa	2	4	A	33	TK184505	Desain Alat Industri Kimla	5	4	В	11				+	
-		Analytical Chemistry						Chemical Equipment Design		+	-	1	+		_	-	-
14	TK141231	Analisa & Pengolahan Data	3	2	A	34	TK184604	Komputasi Numerik Teknik Kimla	5	3	A	11	-	The second secon		+	-
-		Data Processing And Analysis						Chemical Engineering Numerical Computation	-	+	1 "	+	+	NOMER:		+	-
15	TK141232	Kırnıa Organik II	3	3	AB	35	TK141462	Teknologi Material	6	3	AB	+	+	10000 0000	-	-	-
-		Organic Chemistry II		Ħ				Materials Technology		+3	- AD	+	1	THE MAN THE MAN THE PARTY OF TH		+	-
16	TK141233	Sistem Utilitas Pabrik	3	2	В	36	TK 184601	Teknik Reaksi Kimia II		3	8	1	- 11	ar Neil Rank   19 NOV 9C30		-	-
		Plant Utility System		1		-		Chemical Reaction Engineering II	- 0	13	- 0	+	1/2	Tuhintias Tekushar balustri dan Rekayasa Sistem 1	-	+	-
7	TK141331	Matematika Teknik Kirnia I	3	3	A	37	TK 184602	Aplikasi Teknik Kirnia II	6	+-		╌	11 3	S DEKAN	-	+	-
	111111001	Chemical Engineering Mathematics I		-		-		Chemical Engineering Application II	- 0	2	AB	╌			-	+	-
16	TK141332	Azas Teknik Kimia I	3	2	AB	20		Operasi Teknik Kimla III	-	-	-	41	X S		-	1	-
10	16.141332	Chemical Engineering Principles 1	13	3	AD	36		Unit Operations III	6	3	В	4	=				
19	TK141322	Proses Perpindahan I	3	3		20				-	-	1		W/X		1	
	16141033	Transport Processes i	3	3	A	39		Dinamika dan Pengendalian Proses	6	4	AB			Dr. Waway Aries Widodu, ST. MT.			
20	D/141224	Kimia Fisira	-			-		Process Dynamic and Control									
4			3	4	A	40		Manajemen Proyek	6	12	2 AB		11	NIP 97104051797021001			
+	-	Riyocal Chemistry		1				Project Management		1			1	Manual Sea		1	T
_										1	1		-	Jumiah Kredil / Total of Credits	1	49	1

Cat	Catalan Nilai / Grade Explanation (Points						
A	Istimewa / Excellent (4)						
AB	Baix Sekali / Very Good (3.5)						
8	Baix / Good (3)						
BC	Curup Baik / Sufficient (2.5)						
C	Culsip / Fair (2)						
D	Kurang / Poor (1)						
E	Kurang Sekali / Very Poor (0)						

Kode

Tugas Akhir / Final Project Pra Desain Pabrik Metanol Dari Gas Alam Preliminary Plant Design of Methanol from Natural Gas Reserves Pembirmbing / Advisor Prof. Dr. & Ali Altway, M.Sc. Fadhlatul Taufany ST, Ph.D.

Surabaya, 4 September 2020

Dr. Wawan Aries Widodo, S.T., M.T. FT-IRS NIV 197104051997021001

AK/I

PENDIDIKAN FORMAL

SARJANA (S1)

: TEKNIK KIMIA

Th. 2020

KETERAMPILAN

ERANG

MNAS TEMAGA KERJA DAN TRANSAGGRASI

MMAIDI, MM 0701 1 004





DAN TRANSMIGRASI

## PEMERINTAH KABUPATEN SERANG DISNAKER KAB.SERANG JL. KH. FATAH HASAN NO.25 SERANG, PROVINSI BANTEN TELP: 0254 200589

## KARTU TANDA BUKTI PENDAFTARAN PENCARI KERJA

No. Pendaftaran Pencari Kerja : 3604 - 12265 - 23/12/2020

: 3604092708980001 No. Induk Kependudukan Nama Lengkap

> Tempat / Tgl. Lahir : SERANG / 27-08-1998 Jenis Kelamin

: M ILHAM: ALI

: LAKI-LAKI

Status

: BELUM KAWIN

Agama

: ISLAM

Alamat

: TAMAN CIRUAS PERMAI BLOK E1 NO 31, KEC CIRUAS, KAB

SERANG, BANTEN

Telp/Hp

KEC. CIRUAS, KAB. SERANG, PROV. BANTEN

Berlaku s.d

: 081296105302

: 23/12/2022



# CERTIFICATE OF ACHIEVEMENT

This is to certify that

## MUHAMMAD ILHAM ALI, S.T

achieved the following scores on the

## **TOEFL ITP® Test**

Listening Comprehension: 56
Structure & Written Expression: 47
Reading Comprehension: 58
Total: 537

Under the auspices of: LBI FIB UI

At: JAKARTA,Indonesia

**Date:** 08 Oct 2021 Bronze: 09853431 Mohammad Kousha

Mohammad Kousha General Manager Global Education Division, ETS